*calm breathing*
(Forster) Breathe calmly.
In...
*deep inhale*
And out.
*deep exhale*
In.
*deep inhale*
And out.
*deep exhale*
There...
And now...
*eerie music*
Fix your eyes on the pendulum.
Do not try to order your thoughts.
Simply let them go.
And breathe in calmly...
*deep inhale*
...and out.
*explosion, dramatic music*
(Forster) I will guide you.
Step by step.
Step by step,
down to the root of the suffering.
Debout!
- To the source of the pain.
*light switch clicks*
(Forster) Now focus
all your strength
and direct it
upon the stone in your hand.
Your hand obeys your will.
Your will
can crush that stone.
*whimpering*
To your will alone
does your hand submit.
And when you open your hand now,
you will see,
your hand is as calm as mine.
Breathe in calmly...
*music intensifies dramatically*
...and out.
And when I say 'now',
you will let go.
Now.
*he starts up*
*music fades out*
*soft rustling*
How can I ever thank you, Doctor?
*distant rumbling*
How far did you get in your studies,
as an assistant doctor?
Emergency exam in the second year of war.
Then the Western Front.
Why don't you lend me a hand
here at the clinic for a while?
Until you have fully recovered
and I have to let you go.
I could use someone like you.
Comrades,
it is my duty to inform you,
that today
our Kaiser Wilhelm has abdicated.
He and his family have fled the country.
In Berlin, the Social Democrat Scheidemann
has proclaimed the Republic.
After four years of bloodshed,
the war is over.
(Soldier) What will become of us?
Germany has surrendered.
That is not true!
(Hitler) That's a lie!
Lies, all of it!
(Doctor) Silence.
You traitors!
You Jew-ridden scum!
- Come along.
Lies, all of it!
You liars!
- Sit down.
(Hitler) You traitors!
You Jew-ridden... scum!
(mumbles) Miserable rabble.
You will crawl in the dirt,
you filthy worms...
(Anno) Can he be helped?
He won't last long around here,
the troublemaker.
(Forster) His eyes
are completely intact.
Yet he truly sees nothing?
The man does not wish to see.
We call it hysterical blindness.
The cause is not organic in nature.
- A malingerer.
A sick man.
Sick, but not blind.
Hey! Lance Corporal?
Staff Surgeon, Professor, sir.
Come over here.
Over here.
Why are you still awake?
Can't sleep, Professor, sir.
Not for weeks.
Nerves, is it?
A bit frayed?
Please, Staff Surgeon, sir,
help me.
I want to be able to sleep again.
Go into the anteroom
and wait for me there.
Thank you, Professor, sir.
When...?
- Let him wait.
*man speaking in background*
A good subject,
yet full of obstinacy.
We'll let him wait.
(Anno) All night?
- Yes. He must want it.
He must yearn for it with every fiber
of his body
and his soul.
Let him hope all night
that we will come.
He isn't ready yet,
but tomorrow morning we shall release him.
*tense music*
(Forster)
In every man lies a god.
That is the will.
That is the energy.
The flame.
Do you see the flame?
I want to, but...
Yes.
- You must see.
Anything is possible for you.
More!
More.
- *Hitler cries out*
*music subsides*
Good, that's good!
Stand up.
What do you see now?
White? Paper? I...
I see white...
*Hitler pants*
You see.
*eerie music*
*rhythmic music*
*excited chatter,
street noise*
*opulent orchestral music*
Thank God, there you are.
Only you can testify to my information.
Down there at the bar
is Editor-in-Chief Heymann.
We'll speak with him.
- No.
You cannot trust him anymore.
There is a warrant out for your arrest.
Anno, what is going on here?
There he stands, up there.
We must leave right this minute.
*music intensifies dramatically*
*dynamic music*
*music fades out*
(Blank) Come on. Up and around.
*tense music*
Anno, what is going on?
Gereon, his knowledge
has more explosive power than any bomb.
Come on.
*engine starts*
Up ahead.
In Germany, no one will publish
your story anymore.
Certainly not now
that you are wanted by the police.
You must go abroad, immediately.
The express train to Paris
departs shortly.
You have to catch it.
I will get in touch
with Dr. Ernst Weiß.
He is familiar with your story.
He has all the necessary
connections to the press.
How do you imagine this working?
The police are hunting me.
I won't even make it onto the train,
let alone to France.
I will accompany you.
Why should I trust a policeman?
He is my brother.
Ask for Dr. Weiß
at this establishment.
It's the regular hangout of the Germans
in the 5th Arrondissement.
Tell him everything.
I can verify it at any time.
Put these on.
For cover.
Well?
Searched everywhere.
He must have arrested him.
The doctor?
Then he probably took him
to the Burg, didn't he?
Safe to assume, yes.
*crowd sings boisterously*
A magnificent sight.
The outstretched arms, the shouts of 'Heil'.
The Stahlhelm veterans
raise their arms in salute too.
Just like the SA.
It is a unified whole,
expressed here in its entirety.
*men sing marching song*
*dynamic music*
*clamor of voices, whistle blows*
Make room there.
- Out of the way.
The train is packed, stand back.
- We have to get on this train.
My husband has been picked up.
(Man) Wait!
*chaotic shouts*
I'm sorry. The train is completely full,
nothing to be done.
Conductor!
We are conducting an official transfer
abroad.
My colleague must come along too.
Not alone, unfortunately.
Right away, Detective.
Inspector, thank you.
If you would follow me, please.
Colleague!
*music continues*
Good evening,
pardon the intrusion.
The window seats are requisitioned.
We booked reservations.
Official duty is force majeure.
- This is outrageous.
I must ask you.
A window seat isn't necessary.
Yes it is, Inspector, you shall have it.
I must ask you to stand up.
This is an important prisoner transfer.
We will remain on the train, however.
- Naturally, Monsieur.
I apologize, Madame. Have a good journey.
Good evening.
*door closes*
May I?
Don't worry.
The man is... under control.
(Passenger) Mhm.
- (Conductor) Stand back.
*locomotive bell clangs, hubbub*
We have to get through!
We must reach that train!
(Policeman) Out of the way,
that is an order!
Where is this train heading?
Paris, but you're too late.
Where does it stop?
Along the way, where does it stop?
Only in Cologne,
and after that, not until the border.
Come with me.
*train whistle blows*
*gently driving music*
*door opens and closes*
*music swells menacingly*
*music fades slowly*
How do you know my brother?
I treated him.
At the end of the war.
Later, he completed his doctorate under me.
Faced a brilliant career.
And then he...
Yes,
today one would say 'disappeared'.
Until he suddenly resurfaced
nearly a decade later.
Out of the blue.
Under his new identity
as Dr. Schmidt.
What did he want?
My support.
Your brother saw much of this coming.
I did not;
I refused to see it.
What will you tell this gentleman
in Paris?
What is this about?
A medical file.
Is it about a politician?
I'm sorry.
I am taking considerable risks for your sake.
No, not for mine.
You are doing it for your brother,
aren't you?
There is a secret there too.
I abandoned my brother at the front.
It was only by a miracle that he survived.
That haunts you?
To this day.
I am a psychiatrist, so...
I am well acquainted with war trauma.
Very familiar.
Was Hitler your patient?
Yes, I encountered the current
Reich Chancellor back in Pasewalk,
as his physician.
Back then, he was still
a simple lance corporal.
And?
*eerie music*
The psychiatric examinations have...
shall we say, they are of a compromising nature.
And above all,
and far worse for him,
it starkly contradicts his own mythmaking.
What did you want at the Press Ball?
To meet a journalist.
To give him the file?
The file has been gone without a trace
for years,
yet if you will...
I am the file.
*mysterious music*
Gereon?
*music fades out*
*rails squealing*
*dark music*
*distant howl*
(Policeman) Routine check,
papers please.
Routine check, papers.
Routine check, papers please.
Good evening, ladies and gentlemen.
Excuse me, identification please.
(Passenger) We haven't even
reached the border yet.
Routine check, papers!
*somber music*
Kracauer.
You are Jewish?
What does that have to do with anything?
- Yes or no?
Who are you, anyway?
- Please, Eleanor.
(Frau Kracauer) If I have to identify myself,
so should he.
Please pardon my wife.
And yes, I am Jewish.
My wife took my name.
Herbert, you must...
- Be quiet!
(Herr Kracauer) We are traveling
to my sister's in Paris.
We will return next week.
Hm. You Jews have relatives
all over the world, don't you?
What is going on here?
And you are?
Prussian Police.
We're in Thuringia here.
One can tell.
As far as I know, there is no border
between Prussia and Thuringia.
Or did I miss something?
Wise guy, eh?
Identify yourself,
and I will file a formal complaint against you.
*he exhales sharply*
*music subsides*
Thank you.
*Herr Kracauer weeps*
I have no papers on me.
We'll never get to France like this.
*music fades out*
Then we will get off in Cologne.
I can procure papers for you there.
*lively music*
*train whistle sounds loudly*
*music becomes more dynamic*
(Conductor) Stand back!
*clamor of voices*
*Rath laughs*
Rose Monday.
We've arrived just in time.
Or not.
*music fades out*
*excited chatter*
Other exit. Come along.
Now what?
*suspensefully pulsing music*
Out the back. I'll follow.
Erwin.
- (Erwin) Our suitcase!
Conductor! Conductor!
Our suitcase! A thief!
Right, let's go.
Officers! This way!
Move.
- There they are up ahead. Halt!
I said halt!
(Policeman) End of the line, gentlemen!
Put it down. Is that your suitcase?
What is inside?
I haven't the faintest idea.
Hands where I can see them, gentlemen.
*bells tolling*
*cheerful carnival music*
(Policeman) Name?
Rath.
First name?
Gereon.
Date of birth?
March 5th, 1899, in Cologne.
Can you identify yourself?
Unfortunately, no.
I would ask you
to telephone the Police President.
*he chuckles incredulously*
Engelbert Rath. My father.
*distant carnival music*
You refuse to tell me what information
you possess?
I am not permitted to.
You are bound by doctor-patient confidentiality.
I may only share it with colleagues.
Then I cannot procure papers for you.
Your acquaintance with my son
will not avail you either.
I had hoped
you would use your contacts
with the Lord Mayor.
I cannot drag the Mayor into something
whose background I do not know.
Then I must do it.
Do what you must.
Perhaps I should remind him
of that unsavory affair.
What affair?
*mysterious piano music*
The one for which you sent me to Berlin
in the first place.
The Lord Mayor of Cologne is being blackmailed.
Dr. Adenauer.
*projector rattles*
The matter is unsavory.
Must be resolved before the election.
*phone rings*
*tense music*
*phone rings repeatedly*
Yes, go ahead.
*music fades out*
Good day.
Detective Inspector Ritter,
Department A,
Berlin Police Headquarters.
This concerns your son,
Inspector Gereon Rath.
He was last seen
on January 30th around 9 PM
during a police operation
in the company of a murder suspect.
Since then, all trace is lost.
What is your question, miss?
Have you heard from him?
No.
Not for years.
Thank you.
(Engelbert)
A Miss Ritter from Berlin.
She seems to miss you.
Our departure from Berlin was...
well, sudden.
You can't see the Mayor looking like that.
Not today on Rose Monday.
Frau Hülsenbeck!
Connect me with Berlin 1347.
(Kölsch) Hurry it up, you handsome devils,
or you'll miss the whole show.
Thank you.
There, this will suit you.
*he laughs*
Out of the question.
If you want to reach France,
you need papers.
Not dressed like this, however.
*speaker talks indistinctly*
(Forster) I am not wearing that.
If you want to meet the Mayor,
you have to wear one of these.
(Woman)
No answer in Berlin.
Thank you,
I'll try again later.
Lucky Frau Hülsenbeck could round this up
so quickly.
Come here,
give me a carnival peck.
Right, now let's have another drink, eh?
Here's cheers!
*cheers*
(Announcer) Ladies and gentlemen,
the city rises to the thunder of drums.
The squares are ablaze with light,
and laughter hangs in the air like a promise.
From Alter Markt to Heumarkt,
revelry rolls through the streets.
Music surges,
footsteps become rhythm,
motion turns into ecstasy.
This is no mere moment,
this is an event.
Come on.
Where?
We'll take a shortcut.
It's Carnival, it's Cologne,
and now the feast begins!
*carnival music, cheers*
*amused laughter*
Up you go.
*Forster groans with effort*
*festive shouts*
Kölle!
(Forster) We're losing sight of our goal,
Inspector.
There it is.
There is the brewery.
Over here, that's where the Mayor is sitting.
Don't be shy.
*patrons sing 'Einmal am Rhein'
by Willi Ostermann*
# Once on the Rhine,
with a glass of wine in the pale moonshine #
you believe the whole world is thine #
# Your lips will laugh at any hour,
your ailing heart regains its power #
# Come, let me invite you,
once on the Rhine #
*song continues*
*singing in background*
(Adenauer in Kölsch dialect)
Saint Gereon in the flesh.
You bring me joy, my boy.
Herr Mayor.
Father.
Kölle Alaaf!
Here's the situation...
Papa has already filled me in.
You can fly with me to Paris tomorrow,
yes, at 8 o'clock sharp.
I'm flying in an aeroplane,
must be back by evening.
Thank you very much, Dr. Adenauer.
When Papa says it's a must,
then it's a must, isn't it?
It all works out in the end, boy.
Cheers!
We're flying to Paris.
What?
Yes.
Tomorrow morning at eight.
Yes, we're in Cologne.
Everything works out here.
*eerie sounds drown out carnival music*
Yes, operator?
SA Barracks Ehrenfeld, quickly.
*carnival fanfare*
And now welcome with me
the new Reich Chancellor,
today in the dignified company
of Herr Otto Regensburger.
Thank you. Thank you.
Don't get your hopes up too soon,
Herr Hitler and I...
- (Puppet) Regensburger!
*audience laughs*
Don't you dare associate yourself with me.
Yes, but...
- We are the opposite of common.
You are entirely right,
Herr Reich Chancellor.
I've been trying to do that for a long time—
I mean, not to be common.
*laughter*
I mean, associate with you.
- Ah.
He always acts as if he doesn't know me.
I don't know you at all.
Let go of me!
Yes.
That's going to be tricky,
Herr Reich Chancellor.
That is an order!
(Regensburger) Wonderful!
Ladies and gentlemen,
I told you before,
don't get your hopes up too soon.
What do you mean,
don't get your hopes up?
The people are delighted!
Thousands of laughs!
Just for me!
- (Regensburger) No,
that last one was meant for me!
- What?
*astonished murmurs*
You're a Jew!
Circumcised.
*laughter, carnival fanfare*
You're entirely right,
Herr Reich Chancellor.
I, on the other hand...
Yes, you on the other hand?
- Yes, I on the other hand...
*roars of laughter*
(Regensburger) Thank you very much.
Today the Herr Reich Chancellor
will grace us with a reading,
from his book.
*boos*
Yes, a polemic...
(Puppet) Mein Kampf!
- (Woman) Get the hell out of here!
*indignant shouts*
Please, please, quiet!
Quiet please, ladies and gentlemen!
Here is a guest so enthusiastic that he...
*festive music*
Out with it, yes!
Alaaf!
*music plays softly in background*
Well...
*guests hum along to melody*
*glasses clinking*
Dr. Forster, we have to go.
The SA is back there. Out of here.
*music slows down*
*powerful drumbeats*
*music continues*
*quiet, inaudible dialogue*
...summoned to Paris.
In eight hours, the Schnüsse Tring meets.
Well, what do the French understand
of the good life anyway.
See to it that you're back home in time
for the election,
to stop that narcissistic rabble.
Am I right, Gereon?
(muffled) Gereon, am I right?
(muffled) Luckily you just survived
the massacre, my boy.
*engine roar drowns out Adenauer*
Monsieur Fiquet,
it is a pleasure to see you.
Weather isn't great today,
but that's no different in Cologne, is it?
We have little time, unfortunately.
*interpreter speaks French*
Urgent official business awaits me in Cologne.
I must be back by evening.
*interpreter speaks*
*Fiquet speaks French*
With the French, one must always reckon
with the weakness of the flesh.
Allow me to introduce myself.
Eduard von Kittlitz,
German Embassy, Paris.
Your companions,
Herr Lord Mayor,
I fear...
I have directives from Berlin,
Your Excellency. Here.
*interpreter speaks*
From the Reich Ministry of the Interior.
Reich Minister Göring, with respect.
I must ask you to follow me.
Hold on, Herr Kittlitz,
one moment please.
I need to examine
what you have handed me first.
*ominous music*
Very well. These gentlemen come with me,
they are part of my delegation.
No, no.
- Monsieur Fiquet.
Would you be so kind
as to inspect their papers now?
I would be very grateful.
Kittlitz, good day to you.
Inspector, Professor, come with me.
You take the red motorcar.
*man speaks French*
*car starts*
I do not understand your language.
*music fades out*
*bells tolling,
distant chatter*
*somber music*
Merci.
*French conversations in background*
*street sounds*
*French conversation*
(MC in German)
Paris is Berlin.
Pardon.
*singing in French*
Dr. Weiß?
Are you Dr. Weiß?
- With whom do I have the honor?
Edmund Forster. A pleasure.
Who is this?
- Inspector Rath.
He guided me here, thankfully.
I will not speak with a police officer,
let alone one from Germany.
No.
Dr. Weiß,
Inspector Rath risked a great deal
to bring me here to you.
We can trust him.
Rath, did you say?
I believe you knew my brother,
Anno Rath.
He studied under Dr. Forster in Berlin.
Anno Rath is your brother?
Yes, he sent us to you.
Anno Rath is dead.
It's complicated.
(Forster) Yes.
Thank you.
- Would you like something to drink?
Most gladly.
Yes, please.
Mademoiselle.
When did you last see my brother?
In August '24, during that fateful lecture,
when your brother presented
his doctoral dissertation.
...which illustrates the impact our research
can have on politics as well.
*sinister music*
Currently, the Munich Public Prosecutor's Office
must decide
whether the man imprisoned after his coup
last year,
Adolf Hitler,
may be released early
from fortress confinement.
For this reason, Senior Prosecutor
Dr. Martin Dresse
approached our faculty
and requested an expert psychological assessment.
Lance Corporal Hitler,
photographed here shortly after his admission
to the Pasewalk Reserve Hospital
in October 1918.
Blinded, by his own account,
by a British mustard gas shell.
His treating psychiatrist,
Dr. Edmund Forster,
identified Hitler in the clinic
as a hysteric,
who, through auto-suggestion,
fantasized himself into imaginary blindness.
*door opens*
In his clinical report...
*screams of agony*
*acid hisses*
*dramatic music*
Hence your scars.
Yes.
I always saw this as a reminder
of my former hospital comrade.
The scars remind me of him.
For many years, every single day.
After that attack, you changed your name.
Yes.
He must believe that I died.
(Weiß) Who would have thought
that the medical history
of an insignificant Austrian corporal
would prove to be of such decisive significance?
My brother said you possess
trusted connections
to influential French daily newspapers.
Indeed.
The press has been waiting for a story like this.
Yes. The world must learn as quickly
as possible
whom they are dealing with in Germany.
That is true.
Yet whether that will deter our countrymen
from voting for the man,
I venture to doubt.
The brutality with which they attempt
to keep this information secret
speaks of profound alarm
within the NSDAP.
Good. Then we should get straight to work.
From now on, he is under my protection.
Understood.
Come, there is a back exit.
Gereon, thank you, and...
take care of yourself.
Good luck.
*glasses clinking*
Farewell.
This way.
*quiet background chatter*
*sinister music*
Why did Gereon never tell me about you?
Because knowledge of my existence is dangerous.
*sigh*
For everyone.
*applause*
(Guests) Bravo.
*laughter*
*echoing splashing*
*jazz music with spoken singing*
*"Zu Asche, Zu Staub"
by Severija Janušauskaitė*
*applause*
# To ashes, to dust #
# Stolen from the light #
# Yet not just yet,
miracles wait until the end #
*ethereal sounds*
*audience claps along*
# Ocean of time #
# Eternal law #
# To ashes, to dust #
# To ashes,
yet not just yet #
*singer vocalizes*
# To ashes, to dust #
# Stolen from the light #
# Yet not just yet #
# Miracles wait until the end #
*singer vocalizes soulfully*
# It is but a dream #
Mere chasing after the wind
# Who knows for certain? #
# The clock upon your wall #
# Is filled with sand #
# Place your hand in mine #
# And let us be eternal #
# Now you make your choice #
# Casting us
between bliss and torment #
# Yet can I forgive you #
# You are so near to death #
# And yet your gaze so clear #
# Recognize me, I am ready #
# Seeking immortality #
*ominous music*
(Woman) Bravo!
*women laugh uproariously*
*gun clicks*
Good evening, Inspector Rath.
*